<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A friend to navigation plainely expressing to the capacity of the simpler so[rt] the whole misery or foundation of the same art for whose sake, the author hath onely penned this treatise, being himselfe a faithfull good willer thereto.</title>
            <author>Skay, John.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1628</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 82 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 24 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2014-11">2014-11 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A12274</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 22592</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S101969</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99837772</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99837772</idno>
            <idno type="VID">2114</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A12274)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 2114)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1035:01)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A friend to navigation plainely expressing to the capacity of the simpler so[rt] the whole misery or foundation of the same art for whose sake, the author hath onely penned this treatise, being himselfe a faithfull good willer thereto.</title>
                  <author>Skay, John.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[6], 34, [4] p. : table  </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>By T.C[otes],</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>Printed at London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1628.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Dedication signed: Iohn Skay.</note>
                  <note>Printer's name from STC.</note>
                  <note>Print faded and show-through; pages torn and stained; tables of sines, tangents, etc., at end, partly illegible.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the Lambeth Palace Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Navigation --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2013-07</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-08</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-10</date>
            <label>Enrique Valdive</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-10</date>
            <label>Enrique Valdive</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:2114:1"/>
            <p>FRIEND TO NAVIGATION Plainely expreſsing to the capacity of the ſimpler ſo the whole miſtery or foundation of the ſame Art, for <hi>whoſe ſake, the Author hath onely penned this Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſe,</hi> being himſelfe a faithfull good willer thereto.</p>
            <figure>
               <figDesc>woodcut of ship</figDesc>
            </figure>
            <p>Printed at <hi>London,</hi> by <hi>T.C.</hi> 1628.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="illustration">
            <pb facs="tcp:2114:2"/>
            <p>
               <figure>
                  <figDesc>drawing of astrological map</figDesc>
               </figure>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:2114:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>TO ALL THE MOST NOBLE AND GE<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>NEROVS SEAMEN of <hi>England,</hi> happineſſe in <hi>this life, and eternally in the</hi> Heauens.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">V</seg>Rania hauing brought mee (Right Noble) to the ſight of your moſt admirable Art, I could not chooſe but ſay, none could doe ſo great a worke, but the maker of all things. And ſeeing it framed of ſo many excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent peeces, to ſay; none but the Diuine pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uidence can vphold it: Whereupon I endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uoured to inable my ſelfe in ſome knowledge thereof; and (though poore) I Purchaſed ſome bookes, and in diuers yeares beſtowed much mony; imploying my <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> houres that I could
<pb facs="tcp:2114:3" rendition="simple:additions"/> ſpare in this ſtudie and practiſe. And in the meane time, much ſickneſſe, and death of my friends, bringing mee vnder<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap> intollerable bondage <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap>, made me come neerer this Honourable City; but with the loſſe of almoſt my whole eſtate: and in the way had both my Bookes and goods, all loſt and ſpoyled in the <hi>Thames</hi> water. Neuerthe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe (although almoſt vtterly vnabled and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>n<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>learned) I haue not ceaſed to do good if poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible I might (knowing that no man is borne for himſelfe.) Therefore I ſet forth in a bill at my dore, to Teach the Art of <hi>Nauigation,</hi> to the poorer ſort <hi>gratis:</hi> And not ſo content I haue here framed a good order there of (as I think) to ſend abroad to thoſe that cannot come to me. May it pleaſe you therefore vnder your fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uourable <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> direction, to admit it your preſence once onely: to aske you leaue, and to giue you account what I doe among your ſeruants as is moſt meete. And for your fauourable entertainement of it, your <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect to me for my good will, and your kinde acceptance, I reſt,</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>
                  <hi>Your Honours ſeruant to be commanded,</hi> Iohn Skay.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:2114:3"/>
            <head>To the Ignorant and Honeſt Reader.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">H</seg>Oneſt Reader, this worke in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended for thy good, diſpiſe not, but rather accept it thankeful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, ſeeing if it were better I <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ould haue giuen it vnto thee; and more, while J liue I reſt allwayes ready to do thee what good J may. Thou haſt here <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> Chapters: The firſt is of the Coſmographicall diſcription of the world: The ſecond is of the meaſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>re of the heauens: The third of the Elements: The fourth is of the ground of the Art, The Jnstrument, Aſtronomicall propoſitions, with the Geographicall <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap>, and Hidrographi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>call deſcription of the Earth and S<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>a: The fift Chap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter is of certaine conſiderations briefly ſet do<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ne: The ſixt is of Shipping and going out of the Harbour: The
<pb facs="tcp:2114:4"/> ſeuenth of the iournall obſeruation and proiection. The eight and ninth is of propoſitions of Nauigation Arithmetically, Geometrically, and Jnſtrumental<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſhewed: The tenth is of the motion of the Moone, and of comming into the Harbour. Jf thou profit by it, giue God the glory, to whom be praiſe for euer, Amen.</p>
            <closer>
               <salute>Vale,</salute> 
               <dateline>From my houſe in Saint <hi>Thomas</hi> Spittle, <date>May the firſt, <hi>1628.</hi>
                  </date>
               </dateline>
               <signed>Iohn Skay.</signed>
            </closer>
            <trailer>
               <figure>
                  <figDesc>drawing of geometric equation</figDesc>
               </figure>
            </trailer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:2114:4"/>
            <head>A FRIEND OF <hi>NAVIGATJON.</hi>
            </head>
            <div n="1" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. I.</hi> Of the Coſm<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>graphicall diſcription of the World.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>Hat which the onely wiſe God made f<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> mans behoofe, euen all the world of nothing, <hi>Geneſis</hi> the firſt, is ſaid to be round by all moderne Writers: it is proued by reaſon, and the holy Scripture ſaith it, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 98. It was di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uided in two parts by the ſame God, the part ſeene, and the part vnſeene: But by faith ſearch the Scriptures, there is the part and vſe in this our Chriſtian Nauigation diſcouered.</p>
               <p>The part ſeene is well defined to bee a Booke, In which wee may ſee and learns to praiſe God in his workes. And is ſaid to bee of two parts, Celeſtiall, and Elementall: In the Celeſtiall part may be conſidered the Arts, as Muſicke, the harmony of the Spheres: of Soule and Body, for whoſe health Phiſicke is next, in which we conſider that Miraculous Medicine of preſeruing life, be it Philo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſopher ſtone, Salt, Virgin-earth, or other denomination, or Mathe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maticall, as the knowledge of Points, Lines, Circles, Signes, Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtelations, Planets, and their Influence and power ouer bodies Ele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentall.</p>
               <p>It may be ſaid and that by good reaſon, I ſhould begin at the Centor of the Earth, &amp; ſo conſider of the things contained there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in,
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:2114:5"/> with the Sea, The face of the Earth and Sea, and the things thereon; The Aire couering the other two, and the Fire incloſing them all, making one round body of theſe Elementall parts, being as a Centor to the reſt, and ſo p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>e vpwards vnto the firſt m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>er, ſhewing the relation and agreement they haue together, I liuing now nearer the Centor of the Earth (as it is obſerued) by many thouſand miles. But if I end my worke ſo high may bee proud (as ſome are) or dazelled in the Celeſtiall brightneſſe, being mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tall, be caſt downe with <hi>Pl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="4 letters">
                        <desc>••••</desc>
                     </gap>.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>In the name of God therefore, and in his feare, I will begin with the firſt mouer, which going with great violence, turneth the whole frame of the heauen within it, round in 24. houres, from Eaſt to Weſt: Which heauen is ſaid to haue no impreſſion in it, being almoſt inviſible, yet carrying the light and darkneſſe, making differ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>nce of time in daies and nights, according to the difference of Longitude and Latitude of places on Earth.</p>
               <p>In it are all the circles and points in the whole fabricke of the world ſaid to be deſcribed, their plaines defending and meeting in the Centor of the Earth, or on their other Centors.</p>
               <p>The two principall points, are the two poles of the world, the North pole eliuated with vs heere at <hi>London</hi> 51. degrees, 30. or there about; and the South pole is right oppoſite to it. There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore depreſſed iuſt as much (vnder the horizon of which I will ſpeake anon.) Theſe <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> points are fixed faſt and vnmoueable, betweene which and through the Centor of the Earth, there paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> right line, which is called the Axe-tree of the world on which it turneth.</p>
               <p>Now we muſt conſider both this right line, and all other right lines, cords, ſignes, great circles and paralels, to be diuided into 360. degrees, each degree ſubdiuided into 60. minutes, each minute into 60. Seconds, each Second in 60. thirds, &amp;c. as the caſe may re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quire.</p>
               <p>The Herman is a great circle, whoſe Centor is in the middeſt of the Earth, and his plaine reacheth not onely to the face of the Earth, diuiding the vpper part from the lower, the day from the nights <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ut through the Or<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> of the planits and fixed ſtarres, euen to the firſt mouer. This circle hath two poles, one is called <hi>Zon<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>th,</hi>
                  <pb n="3" facs="tcp:2114:5"/> and is right ouer our head, from the which if a right line paſſe through the Center of the Earth, touching the concaue ſuper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficies of the firſt Mouer, it pointeth out the other Pole, called Mador. In this Circle we count the Amplitude of the Sunne or Starres; and the Point of the Compaſſe or Wind. All the Circles called Azimuthes, croſſe the Horizon at Rectangles and paſſe through the Poles thereof: His Parallels are Circle<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> of Altitude, in which are obſerued the poſition of the Planets and fixed Starres aboue the Earth, at all howres of the day or night: Or Circles of Depreſion diuiding the length of twilight.</p>
               <p>The Equator is a great Circle, deuiding the World into two equall parts, the North part and the South: His parallels ſets out the Latitude of places on Earth, and declination in the Heauens. All the Meridians doe croſſe the Equator at Rectangles and go through the Poles of the World. On this is counted the Lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gitude of places on the Earth or Sea: For euerie 4 of equall time made by the equall motion of the Equator doth make 1 degree. And 7 deg. 30 min. of Longitude, either Eaſt or Weſt, doth cauſe <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> houre difference in time of day or night, and they that dwell 15, or 30 deg. Eaſt haue it 12 or 11 a clocke, when we haue it 10 or 11, and thoſe that dwell ſo much Weſt of vs, haue it 10 or 11 when it is midnight with vs. Theſe that dwell at the Eaſt part of our Horiſon haue it noone when it is but 6 in the morning with vs, and when it is noone with vs, it is 6 at night with them, but with them in the Weſt part of our Horizon it is 6 in the morning. Our Antipodes haue it <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>oo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e when it is midnight with vs, and when it is Summer with vs, it is Winter with them.</p>
               <p>All other Circles not yet named are likewiſe ſuppoſed to bee in the firſt Heauen, as in the reſt of the inferior Orbes of which we ſuppoſe 11 after <hi>Maginus.</hi> And to good purpoſe: For the Lord of Heauen and Earth hath ſo layd the Foundations of the Earth that they cannot be moued, <hi>Pſ.</hi> 14.2. Though <hi>Co<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="5 letters">
                        <desc>•••••</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </hi> to bring ſome good purpoſe about hath imagined ſo.</p>
               <p>Let the tenth Heauen be (if you pleaſe) the Wa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ers aboue the Firmament, for ther are ſo, <hi>Gen.</hi> 1.6, 7.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="chapter">
               <pb n="4" facs="tcp:2114:6"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. II.</hi> Of the meaſure of the heauens</head>
               <p>THe Zodiaque is a great broad circle croſing the heauens, like a b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>n<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>re or girdle, of 12<hi rend="sup">d</hi>. broad at the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>eaſt; in the mideſt <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>hereof is a little circle called the ecliptique line, which croſſeth the Equator at two oppoſit points, ſwar<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>eth from it 23<hi rend="sup">d</hi>. 30. at the leaſt, as I ha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ound by obſeruation this preſent yeare 1627. So the poles of the Ecliptique are diſtant from the poles of the world 23<hi rend="sup">d</hi>. 30. by reaſon of his obliquitie: Betweene which poles there paſſeth a right liue or Axetree on which the ſecond <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ouer or tenth heauen is carried in his owne motion (contrary to the firſt) from Weſt to Eaſt, and is moſt ſlowe, making his re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uolution in 3434 yeares, and 10. daies.</p>
               <p>The third mouer or ninth heauen, hath his two poles in the two po<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ts of the equator and ecliptique, and his motion is from North to South: making his reuolution in 1717. yeares and 5 daies. But it will be ſufficient for our neceſſary vſe here to obſerue the moti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of the 8. Sphere, wherein are all the Celeſtiall bodies of the fix<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed Starres placed: whoſe motion is from Weſt to Eaſt, (ſome ſay but one degree in 100. yeare. But the Planets mone in their Or<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>es <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap>, as <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> in 30. yeare, ♃ Iupiter in 12. yeares, ♂ Mars in 2. yeare, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Sol in one yeare, ♀ Venus and ☿ Mercury like ☉, Luna <g ref="char:Moon">☽</g> in a month from Weſt to Eaſt.</p>
               <p>Diuers learned Mathematicions haue ſet downe the magnitude of the Starres to be farre bigger then the earth: making 6. diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rences in bigneſſe be ſides du<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ke and obſcure. The Planets alſo are ſaid to be of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> bigneſſes and diſtances. The Orbe of ♄ is <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> miles, and his diſtance from ♃ 78721 <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> The Orbe of ♃ 189<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>54<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> m. His diſtance to ♂ 78721. m. That of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> 2630<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>800. m. his diſtance from ☉ 15725. m. ☉ 343996 4/<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. m. His diſtance from ♀ 23437 ½ m. The Orbe of ♀ 3274494 6/12. Her diſtance from ☿ 12812. m. ☿ Orbe 253372 <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>/<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. m. His difference from <g ref="char:Moon">☽</g> 12812, The <g ref="char:Moon">☽</g> to be in bignes 105222 <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>/11. her diſtance from the earth 15750. m. ♄ his bigneſſe com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pared to the Earth i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> as 95. to 1. and his diſtance to the Firmament
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:2114:6"/> 2<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>0445. m. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> his magnitude to the Earth is a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> 91. to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. And ♂ as <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. to 1. And the diſtant from the Fir<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ment to the Earth 35 846 3½. m.</p>
               <p>It hath appeared manifeſtly that both by Sea and Land, who ſo trauaileth 60. miles on a great Circle, altereth a degr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e in his Trauaile: which taketh 360. times tho number of the whole cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cle, maketh 21600. miles the conpaſſe of the whole Earthland Sea. The Diameter then will be 6872 <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>/11. the ſemyd<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>amiter 3436 4/1<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> m. which maketh the firmament to be from the Center of the Earth 361899<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>/<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. Therefore it ſeemeth there is ſomething to worke vpon to meaſure theſe things by.</p>
               <p>Likewiſe I may ſay, conſidering that from the earth to the Moone is 15750. miles, and the <g ref="char:Moon">☽</g> is the loweſt Planet. There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the two vppermoſt elements of Ayre and Fire are both to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether 15750 mi. in thickneſſe: Againe, becauſe the hill Atlas is ſaid to reach to the midle region of the ayre, that hill (which I take to be Teneriffe) may eaſily be meaſured, and ſo the mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure of all the reſt is had.</p>
               <p>The motion of the Eclipticke cauſeth other foure circles to be deſcribed, two are deſcribed of the motion of the Poles ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of, being diſtant from the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>es of the world 23. degrees 30. min. making two round circles about them: that next the North pole is called the circle Articke, the other is called the circle Antarticke. The other two are deſcribed by the motion of the tow. Tropicall points of the eclipticke, that on the North ſide of the equanox is called the tropicke of Cancer, the other is cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led the tropicke of Capricorne. The Zodiacke is diuided in 12. equall parts, beginning at the one interſection of the ſame with the equanoctiall circle, and ſo going round: And theſe are called the 12. ſignes of the Zodiacke, for as much as they extend them to the full breadth of the Zodiacke, and are the cauſe thereof.</p>
               <p>There are two other circles alſo of ſpeciall vſe in this Art, one is the Equinoctiall colure, the other is the Solititiall colure: Theſe two are great circles, the firſt parteth the Equator and Zodiacke euen, ſo as the North ſignes are from the South ſignes parted by the firſt point of the firſt ſigne, and the firſt point of
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:2114:7"/> the ſca<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>outh ſigne: and theſe ſignes are called Aries ♈, and Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bra ♎, beginning the Spring and Autumne, the other paſſeth by the two tropicall points of Cancer ♋, and Capricorne ♑, making the beginning of Summer and winter; both paſsing through the poles of the world, parting the Zodiacke in foure equall parts, and the equator alſo with all his paralels.</p>
               <p>The firſt point of ♈, beginneth the Spring: that is, when the Sunne in his motion commeth firſt to that point, and going through three ſignes ♈, Taurus ♉, Gemini ♊: then comming to the firſt point of ♋, beginneth the Summer: and paſsing through other three ſignes ♋ Leo ♌, Virgo ♍, ſo commeth to Libra ♎, Scorpio ♏, Sagitarius ♐, to the firſt point of ♑: be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginneth the winter, from thence through ♑, Aquarius ♒, Piſſes ♓ making the whole yeares reuolution. And theſe 12. ſignes are called Conſtellations, and there are other Conſtellations, ſome North, ſome South, in which is had a number of Starres bearing names, according to their nature: and theſe conſtellati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons beare rule ouer diuers Regions, Countries and Cities.</p>
               <p>Now we may paſſe the Orbes of the other ſuperior Planets, &amp; onely note their friendly aſpect as we paſſe by them: And con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider the <g ref="char:Moon">☽</g> motion with the ☉ for the Eclipſes of vſe, for fin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding of longitude on earth or Sea. Her monthly motion, full change and quarters, for the ebbing and flowing of the waters, ſpring and nepe tides: her aſpect with the planets, good or euill, for Phyſicke: Her place in the Zodiacke, for bloud letting ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther for Man or Beaſt.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>C<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>AP. III.</hi> Of the Elements.</head>
               <p>FIre is the moſt noble and ſuperiour of all the Elements, pure, ſubtle, moſt ſpirituall, putting heat into all ſubſtances, light<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſome, hauing motion Lionous, choloricke. Ayre is diuided into three Regions, that next the Fire is moſt hot, that in the middle moſt cold, vnto the which ſome hill tops doe clime, as hath been ſeene, the loweſt is that in which wee liue, the Clouds and the
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:2114:7" rendition="simple:additions"/> Fowles doe flye, which God of his mercy make wholeſome vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to vs. <hi>God ſaid let the waters vnder heauen be gathered into one place, and let the dry land appeare, Gen.</hi> 1.9. <hi>And God called the dry land Earth, and the gathering together of the waters, he</hi> (euen God) <hi>called Sea, ver.</hi> 10. Sea, which together with the earth make one huge maſsiue body, round, as may be proued by the artificall Globe,: but moſt truely by a perfect Artſman, who vſing his skill in his Trauell, both by Sea and Land, is able to ſalue ſuch ſmall irrigularities, as high tydes, lowe ebbes, high Mountaines lowe Vallies: For experience is the mother of Acts, and th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> partly conceiue in this (I hauing a brother in Saint <hi>Christo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phers</hi> Iſle of the Weſt <hi>Indies,</hi> who hath ſent me Letters from <hi>Meri<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>rs</hi> Hope there) I went to <hi>Greſham</hi> Colledge in <hi>London</hi> of purpoſe to looke on the biggeſt Terreſtriall Globe they had, and found ſuch an Ile to lye in ſome 16. deg. of North Latitude, and in 321 deg. of longitude, or there about: But there I could finde neither Cape, nor Bay, Port nor Hauen; therefore no vniuerſall Map will ſerue that turne: And Maſter ♄, being there with mee at that time, made a doubt, ſaying: How know I that Saint <hi>Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtophers</hi> Ile lyeth there except I had ſeene it, or know ſome body that had bin there? meaning no doubt ſome Arts-man, who (I confeſſe) may not onely obſerue the longitude and latitude; but may alſo ſet out the Capes and Bayes, Ports, Bounds, Riuers, and giue the dimention of the ſuperficis.</p>
               <p>Of the innumerable multitude of creatures in the Sea, and of her riches, I will not ſpeake; but the artificiall making and vſe of Shipping therein is admirable, as may appeare in the whole Art of Nauigation: A wonderfull ſecret thereof is the variation of the compaſſe; a cauſe thereof is imagined to be the hollow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of the Earth or depth of the Sea, and for that nature abhor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring emptineſſe, the excellent vertue of the Load-ſtone doth al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wayes draw towards it in all places, where the needle being touched therewith ſhall draw moſt neere; but I thinke it is a ſpeciall gift of God, ſent for mans vſe, but farre aboue his knowledge. Sea and earth are diuided as the heauens: the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginning of the Equator or firſt Meridian being with Saint <hi>Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chael</hi> and Saint <hi>Maries</hi> Iles, the circle of the equator paſsing by
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:2114:8"/> Saint <hi>Thomas</hi> Ile, <hi>Abaſa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="3 letters">
                        <desc>•••</desc>
                     </gap>,</hi> the famous Ile of <hi>Sa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="3 letters">
                        <desc>•••</desc>
                     </gap>ta, B<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>rni<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>, Pap<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>os, New Guinny, G<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>na<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>s,</hi> and fo round, from Meridian to Meridian Eaſtward we count Longitude on any paralell: but La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titude is counted from the Equator towards the Poles of the World on the Meridian or colure. The Paralels ſets out the Zones and Climates.</p>
               <p>Of creatures without life, or ſuch as are in the earth onely, are Gold, Siluer, precious Stones, Minerals, Mettals. But the Bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies which ſhall one day riſe againe, are chiefely to be conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red. Of Creatures with life, ſome are fixed, as Plants, Hearbes, Flowers, Spices, Trees, bearing fruit, without fruit. <hi>Gen.</hi> 2.19. <hi>Out of the ground God formed beaſts and fowles:</hi> and in another place it is ſaid <hi>All fleſh is graſſe.</hi> Therefore of mouing things ſome are in the Earth, as Wormes, Serpents, Moles, Co<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>e<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>: ſome in the Ayre, as Fowles: in the Water, as Fiſhes. Mon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters on the face of the earth, as all manner of Beaſts and Cattell wilde and tame. The moſt excellent thing made is man (a ſhame for him to become ſo wicked) <hi>Being wonderfully made, Pſal.</hi> 139. an epitomy of the whole World; to ſeeke and ſet forth Gods glory: ſurely fleſh and bloud cannot ſet forth his glory, whoſe workes doe amaze the ſences of the moſt learned. Therefore be not proud O ye learned, nor vaineglorious O ye wiſe; but ſeeke and ſet forth Gods glory, that the vnwiſe and vnlearned, may ſee, marke, and learne: and be incouraged O thou that art igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant (of which I am chiefe) to ſee the workes of the Lord in heauen and in earth, and his wonders in the deepe Sea, <hi>Pſ.</hi> 107.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="4" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>CAHP. IIII.</hi> The gound of the Art, the Inſtrument, Aſtronomycall propoſitions, with the Geographicall and Hidrographicall deſcription of the Earth and Sea.</head>
               <p>REaſon doth teach, and this 36. yeares experience I haue had, that to the gaining of theſe knowledges, quantitie is to bee conſidered, either Geometrically or Arithmetically, or moſt vſual<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly of both together. Arithmeticke is the Art of numbering, and
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:2114:8"/> euery number is expreſſed by certaine Characters, figures, and Ciphers, as: 1, 2, 3, 4, 5, 6, 7, 8, 9, 0. or: 2<hi rend="sup">•</hi>. 3<hi rend="sup">d</hi>. 30. 50. 20l: <expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:powerof3"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>powerof3</ex>
                  </expan>+ <expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:powerof2"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>powerof2</ex>
                  </expan>+ <expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:powerof1"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>powerof1</ex>
                  </expan>=to <expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:powerof5"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>powerof5</ex>
                  </expan>−n. But the figures and Ciphers whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther they be abſtract or contract, haue a double ſignification to expreſſe them, which is called their numeration, Pſal. 90. ver. 12. <hi>O Lord, teach vs ſo to number our daies, that we may apply our hearts vnto wiſedome.</hi> Figures do either ſignifie themſelues onely, as 1. is one, 2. is two, &amp;c. or are valued according to their place: Poſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of this kinde is knowne as men read the Hebrew tongue. This Art giueth the numerall ſolution in all dementions, and hath theſe kindes: Addition, Subtraction, Multiplication, Diuiſion; and theſe all haue a diuers property in their vſe, either in working proportion, or otherwiſe. Another Arithmatique there is (not of numbers) but of parts of number, hauing like ſpecies, proper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties and paſsions, and fetch either their beginning from vnity, but with a difference, for as number increaſeth in multitude Infinit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly: ſo doe Fractions decreaſeth infinitly but moſt com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monly, as in this worke, they are compound: for if I take in account of Time, Motion, Meaſure, Signes, Degrees, Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nut<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>, Seconds, &amp;c. As in reckoning of the <g ref="char:Moon">☽</g> place, Thus: ſuppoſe the <g ref="char:Moon">☽</g> in the day of ♂ to be in the firſt degree of ♈; and a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> 20. daies old, I would know her place; ſay if the <g ref="char:Moon">☽</g> go in one day 12. degrees from the ☉, and the ☉ goe each day one degree, There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the <g ref="char:Moon">☽</g> goes in 20. dayes 260<hi rend="sup">d</hi>. which diuided by 30<hi rend="sup">d</hi>. giueth 8<hi rend="sup">•</hi>: 20<hi rend="sup">d</hi>. where <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. is the number 20, the Fraction, and his place the 20<hi rend="sup">d</hi>. of Sagitarius: But where deg. are taken for numbers, there Minuts, Seconds, Thirds, are Fractions: as 15<hi rend="sup">d</hi>. to an houre 4. to a degree, or 20<hi rend="sup">d</hi>. is as much as one houre 20: or 20<hi rend="sup">d</hi>. 50. 30. is as much as 1250 miles ½: and generally all circles and paralels, are numbered with theſe kinde of Aſtronomicall Fractions or numbers.</p>
               <p>Geometry giueth a punctuall termination to all dementions, ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther in length, bredth, or thickneſſe: which number many times cannot doe; as in diuiding a line by extreame and meane propor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion. But number and parts do helpe Geometry to expreſſe the quantitie, bee it in length, bredth, or thickneſſe. Linne<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>mall as angles right lined, of Sphericall: &amp; may ſerue to tel ſome diſtance
<gap reason="illegible: missing" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="10" facs="tcp:2114:9"/> Inſtruments neceſſary in any worke, are of necesſity, and to this worke which conteineth ſo many Arts, it may be obiected that one poore though of a good capaſsity ſhall be neuer able to attaine. Say not ſo man, for the beſt inſtrument in any worke is a willing minde: Againe, ſhall I be aſhamed to indeuour to doe well, becauſe ſome more learned then I, will deſpiſe my ſimpli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>city and weakeneſſe in knowledge? No ſure, the vertuous will commend it, God bee thanked there are as many good Inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments as Arts, let euery man bee content with ſuch as hee hath, and God no doubt will bleſſe the good indeauours of the godly honeſt. 2<hi rend="sup">s</hi>. 6<hi rend="sup">d</hi>. on a paire of Compaſſes, and two pence on a ſtraight ruler is not much: with theſe thou maieſt beginne in ſpending ſome ſpare houres time to worke thus: firſt make a circle, diuid it in 360. parts, or ¼ into 90, and beſides abundance of neceſſary concluſions, which the malicious ignorant will not beleeue, theſe following are not the leaſt, and are moſt meet to be knowne: Radius or any ſigne, cord, arke, Tangent, Secant, great circle, parralell: example: I did take the ☉ height, <hi>May</hi> the 26. 1627. and ſo found his declination 22<hi rend="sup">d</hi>. 30. North, his place being in 15<hi rend="sup">d</hi> ♊. right aſſention, 61<hi rend="sup">d</hi>. 30. difference aſſenti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>onall 28<hi rend="sup">d</hi>. 15. height of the North pole 51<hi rend="sup">d</hi>. 30. Amplitude 37<hi rend="sup">d</hi>. 30 North. oblique aſſention 33<hi rend="sup">d</hi>. 15.: ſemydiurnall arke 118<hi rend="sup">d</hi>. 15. ſemynocturnall arke 61<hi rend="sup">d</hi>. 45. his courſe from riſing to his ſetting, 15 houres 40. length of twilight 8 houres 14. length of the night darke 0. houre. Likewiſe about December the 12. 1627. ☉ place 0 ♑ merid height 15<hi rend="sup">d</hi>. declination 23<hi rend="sup">d</hi>. 30. South, amplitude 40<hi rend="sup">d</hi>. 30. ſouth, right aſſention 270<hi rend="sup">d</hi>. oblique aſſencion 298. deg. 30, difference aſſencional 28. d. 30. Likewiſe may the fourth 1629. ſuppoſe the ſonnes place which is his lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gitude, found by the rules before going to be 53. d. or the 23. of ♉. in the latitude of 51. deg. 30. min. his merid. height is found by theſe rules to be 55. deg. declination 18. deg. north, amplitude 28. north, right aſſention 50. deg. oblique 27. deg. difference aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſentionall 23. deg. ſemydiurnall arke 7. hou. 32. min. ſemynoctur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall arke 4. hou. 28. min. length of twilight 2. hou. 4. min. from noone to euening ſhut in 9. hou. 33. min. length of the day 19. hou. 6. min. night darke 4. hou. 54. min. Son riſe at 4. hou. 28. m.
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:2114:9"/> ſetteth at 7 hou. and 32. min. Sun aboue the Horizon 1<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> hou. 4 min. vnder the Horizon 8 hou. 56 min.</p>
               <p>And here remember, that, <hi>The workes of the Lord <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>p g<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="4 letters">
                        <desc>••••</desc>
                     </gap> ſought out of all them that haue pleaſure therein. Pſ.</hi> 111.2. <hi>The mercifull and gracious Lord hath ſo done his maruilous workes, that they ought to be had in remembrance, v.</hi> 4. <hi>The Lord is high aboue the Heauens, Pſ.</hi> 113.4. <hi>Who is like the Lord our God, that hath his dwelling ſo high, and y<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap> humbleth himſelfe to behold the things that are in Heauen and in Earth, v.</hi> 5. <hi>He taketh the ſimple out of the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>ſt. v.</hi> 6. <hi>The Heauens declare the glorie of God, and the Fir<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="6 letters">
                        <desc>••••••</desc>
                     </gap> ſheweth his handiworke, Pſ.</hi> 19.1. As <hi>Arcturius Orio<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </hi> pleades the hiden Chambers of the South, the great <hi>Lauiathan</hi> that mo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>eth in the water, but beyond all our Redemption in Chriſt, God commanded <hi>Noah</hi> to build an Arke, and to build Shiping were but vaine except God bleſſe it and bee the Sea-mans guide. Say then, is it not a great bleſſing we receiue from him in guiding our Ships and Selues both by Sea and Land with ſuch excellent Rules of Art: Surely the learned in the Geographicall, Hidro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>graphicall and Nauticall Sciences muſt needs confeſſe it, eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially thoſe that trauell.</p>
               <p>Neither need any be ſo ſottiſh as to thinke it a ſhame to ſpend ten min. of his idle time euerie day to ſome ſuch good purpoſe, which may add him more comfort perhaps in diſtreſſe, then all the friends in the world beſides. By the Seale made on a ſtraight Ruler and Compaſſes diſtance is had eaſily without meaſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to them, for make a Circle and diuide it in foure equall parts with ſtraight lines ouer the Centor, then diuide ¼ in two equall parts, and ech of them in 3 then againe theſe ſubdiuiſion<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> in 3 and laſtly thoſe into 5, ſo is one quarter of the Circle diuided in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to 90 deg. by the ſame reaſon you may diuide a right line as your Ruler into Foots, ech Foot into Inches or Tenths, ech 10 into <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> 3. 4. 5. 7. 11. 12. 16. 20 parts or what you pleaſe, and then begin to worke thus, Imagin to ſtand on ſome Hill as at High <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> from thence to all the higheſt Hilles round about you caſt your eye, and by your Circle diuided you may take the quantitie of the Angle from your eye to the two next Hilles from you and neereſt one to another. Suppoſe that Shutors Hill and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>urfleet
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:2114:10"/> Hill doe make an Angle of 1/<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> of the quadrant or 30 deg. Or Har<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row Hill and Saint Albones make an Angle of 40 deg. and the diſtance between High-gate and Shuters Hill to be 10 mil. more or leſſe, and from High-gate to Harrow 12 mil. you ſhall goe to Shuters Hill and obſerue the Angle between High-gate and Pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fleet, be it right or oblique, acut or obtuſe make 2 lines, whereof one to be laid downe by the Scale on your Ruler of the iuſt di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance between your 2 firſt ſtations, at the one end make the firſt Angle, at the other end make the other looking one towards the other, and the two lines continued will point you our Purfleet, doe ſo by the other and it will point you out Saint Albones, then by your Scale you may know their diſtance, hauing them diſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces you may eaſily find all the diſtances and angles of poſition or ſituation of all the Hilles, Townes, Riuers, Borders, in any one Countie, and from thence ye may doe the like by the reſt, and ſo take a true ſu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>eigh of a Kingdome, and of all the Iles, &amp; Rockes in the Sea, and Kingdomes adioyning, as Scotland with his Iles, and ouer the Sea, as Ireland with his Iles, likewiſe from Douer to Callice, and ſo take the Countrey and Kingdome of France, with his Riuers, Iles, Rockes, and euerie remarkeable thing that commeth in view of your eye.</p>
               <p>But note, that if you meaſure ſuch great diſtances, you muſt haue regard to Longitude and Latitude, for if you ſhall meaſure from France to Spaine, Portugale, and ſo ouer the mouth of the St<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> of Guib<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ater into Barbarie, Guiny, by the Coaſt of Saint Thomas Ile, Monomotapa, Cape Good-hope, the Coaſt of Saint Latence, Moſamque, Preſter Iohn, the head of the ancient Riuer Nilus, the Arabian, Iudean, Notalia, Grecian, Italian Countreys, ſo come to Germany, Polonia, and all thoſe North parts to the Pole if you can, or to Sweden, Moſcouia, and the North part of Tartaria, and th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> way diſcou<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>r all the North parts round about the Pole, and ſo if you can come into North America, if not, then come ouer Land neere the Caſpian Sea, Parthia, Perſia, Ormuſe, Guſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap> Goa, Cochin, and all the Iles to the South thereof, the Gulph of Bengala, Malaca, Sumatra, the Strait of Sunda, Iaua maior, Iaua minor, new Ginny, Papoos, Hiland, Timor, ſo to Beach, and to the diſcouerie of the parts of Maletor Kingdome
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:2114:10"/> to the South Pole if you can, or by the Moluce<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e, Bernie, Ca<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bia, Cochin China, Iapan China, to Cathay, from thence Eaſt a little North to the Straits of Annian, and ſo into the moſt Weſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erly parts of North America, Portray all that new world, to be ſhort, come by the Gulph of Mexico down to the Strait of Land called Noua Hiſpaniola to Peru, goe ouer the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>trait of Ma<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nica and diſcouer all the vnknowne Land round about the South Pole.</p>
               <p>Which thing may be done by Gods permiſſion no doubt, and when thou haſt done this moſt truly, with all the Coaſts of the Seas, thou wilt ſay the circompherence of the Sea is alſo had<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> True, yet neuertheleſſe ye ſhall neuer be able to lay the true ſeme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try of both Earth and Sea on a plaine ſuperficies by this way.</p>
               <p>The like may you proue by the Hidrographicall diſcription of the Sea, by the common Sea Card. And here note, that this may ſerue likewiſe to proue that the Earth and Sea make one round Body.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="5" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. V.</hi> Of certaine conſiderations to be remembred, briefly ſet downe.</head>
               <p>AS I conceiue, there are theſe three things to be conſidered, without which fayling cannot be performed. The firſt, is an exact obſeruation of the Sunne, Moone, and Starres. The ſecond, is the perfect finding out of the vari<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>tion of the Compaſſe. Laſtly, a true reckoning of the Ships way. Theſe all doe helps one another, and ſhould be preciſely had. Againe, the Earth and Sea making one round Body, we may conſider that to ſayle be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween 2 places, may be either by a Par<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ll, a Rui<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>, or a gr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap> Circle, as ye may perceiue by the artificiall Globe. Therefore if ye can draw ſome blanke Charts to carrie with you in your voy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ages, ſuch whoſe Meridians and Parralels beare ſuch proportion one to the other in ech Latitude, as thoſe in the Globe, you ſhall doe well.</p>
               <p>In the Globe you may perceiue the degrees in the Equator to agree and be equall with the degrees in the Meridian. Now the
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:2114:11"/> degrees in the Meridians <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> where equal, but the degrees in the Parralels to the Equator are leſſe and leſſe, ſo that a degree of Longitude in the 60 deg. of Latitude is but ½ of that degree of Longitude in the Equator, and as the whole ſigne is to the number of parts in a degree of Longitude at the Equator, ſo is the fight of the complement of any Latitude to a fourth number (by the rule of proportion of geometricall demoſtration) which number tels you how many parts of a degree of the Equator ſerueth a degree of Longitude in that Latitude, but in a plaine Card where the Meridians are all Parralels, there becauſe the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grees of Longitude in ech Latitude are equall, you muſt increaſe the degrees of the Meridian in ech Latitude in ſuch proportion as is aboue ſaid, which is eaſie to be done with the Scale on your Ruler.</p>
               <p>This to looke on to the eye will be ſtrange, and to ſuch as loue to ſt<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>oke to their old errors, in the plaine Card they will thinke it cleane againſt reaſon, but let ſuch deſcribe ſome portion of the world in it, they may compare it with a Globe, and ſee it beare a true ſemetry, but in their plaine Card it will appeare monſtrous. Here is now a view of the world from Centor to Circomference, Here is an entrance to the meanes of obtaining to ſome abilitie in the vſe and practiſe thereof: But aboue all and in all things giue vnto the Lord the glorie due vnto his name, <hi>Pſ.</hi> 29.2. And this indeed is the verie thing wherein we ought to reioyce, and for which God made vs, namely, to ſeeke his glorie, which is wonderfully ſeen: and for forth in the frame of the World, but moſt mightily in the part vnſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap> but by Faith, with which eye thou muſt looke into Heauen by viewing here on Earth Gods holy Word, and hearkening with the eare of Faith, to the Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters of his Word, who doe breake the Bread of Life vnto the faith <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>reable virgins ſtrong meat vnto men, &amp; <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to babes, ſo ſhalt thou be the better able to worſhip the Lord in the beautie of his holineſſe, <hi>Pſ.</hi> 19.2.</p>
               <p>It appeareth, <hi>G<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>.</hi> 1.14. that God made the Lights in the Fir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mament to diuide the day from the night, and to be for ſignes and ſeaſons, dayes and yeeres. And v. 15. to giue light vpon the Earth, according to the roundneſſe of the Earth, and motion of
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:2114:11"/> the ☉ the light and darkeneſſe doe differ, for the Sunnes body being bigger then the body of the Earth, maketh that the Sunne being at the Equator, although from Sunne ryſing to Sunne ſet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting be iuſt 12 howres, yet the light will appeare from breake of day to euening ſhut in 14 h. 24 m. and the darkeneſſe will con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinue 9 h. 36 m. Now if two men be one vnder the North Pole, another vnder the South Pole, they ſhall both ſee the Sunne in their Horizon, if the ☉ decline towards the North, he will riſe aboue the Horizon to him in the North, but to him in the South the ☉ ſetteth and when the ☉ is in the tropicke of ♋ it is noone with him in the North, but with him in the South it is midnight <hi>(&amp; contra.)</hi> By this it appeareth the time betweene Sunne riſing and Sunne ſet to either of them is about 436. houres, on <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>/<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> yeere, ſauing that the Lords louing kindneſſe hath been of old, <hi>Pſa</hi> 5, 6 to this Chriſtian part of the world, in placing the Suns Apoge in this part, by which we receiue a double benefit, the one of light ſo much the longer by the Sunnes ſlow motion, the other, that when the Sun is come ſo neere our Zeneth, it hath pleaſed God to draw it vp neerer Heauen and further from the Earth, that we be not burned with his heat, as it is written, The Sunne ſhall not burne thee by day, nor the Moone by night, Pſ. 121.6. <hi>Et</hi> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> in the South part of the World among the Heathen that know not God. But in the Poles the twilight laſteth ſo long as the Sun is within 18 deg. of the Horizon, which is about the firſt of May, ſo the darke night laſteth 1968 h. and the twilight is about 1200 h. that is 50 dayes with vs. From theſe two differences in a right Spheare you may make to your ſelfe a Theoricke of the oblique by conſidering the difference of light betweene any number of degrees from the Equator to the Poles as you pleaſe, or after this example: I did obſerue the height of the Sunne this yeere 1627, and found him to be more then 62 deg. in Meridian height, proues that the Sun hath more then a <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> deg. 30 min. de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clination, or elſe the Poles eleuation to be leſſe then 51 d. 30 m. here at London, which the learned haue likewiſe proued in the<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> moſt exact obſeruations, but for the leſſe learned, and the honeſt Sea-mans vſe, the declination of 23 d. 30 m. will make no <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>. Now that in a Countrey of knowne Latitude you may fin<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>lly
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:2114:12"/> the height of the Sun his Azimuth and declination in any Longi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude, by which you may find the variation of your Compaſſe at all houres of the day, or by the day of the month the Suns Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ridian height being giuen, is had the Latitude of the place, or height of the Pole, then the amplitude or azimuth as before, and to ſpeake truly, theſe prepoſitions depend on one another, and what is ſaid of the Sun, may likewiſe be done by the Stars being knowne, their Longitude, Latitude, and Declination being like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe had.</p>
               <p>If any man ſhall ſay, I haue diſcouered my wants herein, he ſaith truly, if my malice my good will, let him know I care not, if any man will further my willing mind, to him I will ſend this Boaſte for Patronage, and for euer pray for him, if any fleare and ſcoffe at mee, it were much better for his Soule that he were at prayers, and leaue ſcoffing. Euerie good man may if pleaſe him, amend this, and ſo further me. If no ignorant man will profit by it, yet let ſuch as are honeſtly minded, ſuffer this to liue with me, becauſe all that I haue, or can doe, is but to imploy my time in ſuch meane knowledge as I haue, to Gods glorie, and the benefit of my Countrey. Wherein if knowledge and a purſe did agree with heart and good will, I would ſtriue with the beſt Subiect. In the meane time I will ſtriue to doe my beſt, as my dutie doth bind me.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="6" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. VI.</hi> Of Shipping and going out of the Harbor.</head>
               <p>THeſe things afore ſpoken of, are moſt vſefull, and now I hold it a good method to examine your Ship whether ſhee be for your turne or not, in all things well appointed for the Sea, if new, how well built, and ſtrong, and how well fitted in her ge<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>re, if old, whether ſhe be able to indure the ſurging waues of the Sea, to goe another voyage, and likewiſe for her burthen, proportioned according to the buſineſſe ye vſe her for. But if ye wi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> build a new Ship in any proportion aſſigned, ye ſhall iudge <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> better how to haue it done, by learning ſo much in Arithme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticke,
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:2114:12"/> as to be able to extract the Square and Rube root, then may you doe after this example next following, or otherwiſe at your pleaſure. Let the proportion be as two to one, and ſuppoſe you haue a Ship of 100 tun, in all things ſo well framed, that thou doeſt deſire to haue one of 200 tun, and like to the other to do this, firſt take the meaſures of your firſt Ship, which ſuppoſe to be theſe, the Keele 44 foot, at the Beame 20 foot, in Houle 9, foot, her Rake afore 13 foot, after 7 foot, here is giuen ſixe num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers, and the proportion aſſigned, and ſeeing the proportion is to be doubled, therfore take ech number &amp; cube it, then double that cube number, and extract the cube root of that number, and you ſhall find the ſecond Ship muſt haue in Keele 55½ foot neere, and Beame 25 and about ½, in Houle 11½, Rake afore 16<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>, after almoſt 9, and her burthen will be 200 tun, or this may be found by that excellent Inſtrument of the memorable Maſt. <hi>Edmund Gu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="3 letters">
                        <desc>•••</desc>
                     </gap>r,</hi> lately ſet forth by him in his life-time, and is called a Sector, his proportionall Ruler and Croſſe-ſtaffe is well knowne to bee an excellent Inſtrument for theſe purpoſes following, and alſo for many other, Take in equall parts of the Sector 44, and fit it ouer in the Cubes at 44, the Sector ſo reſting, take with your Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſſes the diſtance ouer in 88 of the Cubes, and apply it to the equall parts, giueth 55½, as before, do ſo by the reſt, and you ſhall find the like numbers.</p>
               <p>But ſay it be demanded to haue her of any other proportion, namely, as 20 to 15, or 4 to 3, take the meaſures of the firſt, an before, and cube them, then ſay, if 15 giue ſuch a Cube, what Cube ſhall 20 giue, it will giue a number, whoſe Cube root in the number ſought. But by the Sector take the numbers <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> &amp;c. in equall parts, and fit them ouer in 15 of the Cubes, then take the diſtance ouer in 20 of the ſame lines, and that applyed to the equall parts, giueth the number ſought.</p>
               <p>And now being fitted with a Ship for thy purpoſe and hauing launched, and going downe the Riuer take heed to the ſet of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> Tyde, not onely for running fowle of other craft, but leaſt ye bring your ſelfe on ground on a Lee ſhore, on a Shelfe, Sand, or Shole, as Barking ſhelfe, a Shole againſt Grayes, Blacke ſhelfe, the Piles below Tilberie, Milton ſhore, or in a darke night gape
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:2114:13"/> for a ſho<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e, and thinke to gaine the point, but run your Ship cleane out of the Thames as I ſee one had done, the 18 Decemb. 1627, and layd her on the March below Greene-hiue in Kent. Going out or in any Riuer whatſoeuer, note what marke yee ſee with the opening of any Point, as Yoke on a Wall, Tree, Houſe, Hill, Wood, Wind-mill, Steeple, Caſtle, or Towne, and learne to deſcribe the Semetry of it, and note it in a Booke, remembring to ſound the depth, and note it likewiſe, and what grounds for ancoring good or bad, with the ſwiftneſſe and indraft or outlet of the waters, ye may alſo deſcribe the windings thereof by the Compaſſe, with the lengths and breadths on a Paper, and be ſure to note the magniticall Azimuth, for your variations, be it of the Sonne or Starres, which to be able to do, learne ſo much in Geo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>metry, as to be able to deſcribe the Spheare in plaine, and to know the vſe of the Globes, or at leaſt to vſe your plaine Scale, and keep your trauice on your Card, &amp; a Iournall or daies Book, and know both in Riuer and at Sea, thou muſt make vſe of theſe two Globes, namely, the Scriptures where the good ſhine like Starres, and Chriſt Ieſus is the true Load-ſtone.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="7" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>CAHP. VII.</hi> Of the Iournall, obſeruation, and proiection.</head>
               <p>VVHen you are come into the Sea, begin your Iournall on this wife: In the Name of God, Amen. The daies Booke for the Voyage intended, for Saint Chriſtophers, and C<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>e de Mine. The 24 of May wee came out of Portſmouth, and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>cored in Stokes Bay. The 25 wee weighed, and with a g<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>e Baſterly. The 26 we put thorough the Needles. The 27 wee put in at Dartmo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>th, the wind South South Weſt, verie fo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>e. And you may make a <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>alender after ſuch like order a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> this.</p>
               <gap reason="illegible: missing" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="19" facs="tcp:2114:13"/>
               <p>heare though I haue ſet but ſome dayes of the mouth: yet I meane you ſhould ſet downe each day, and in the laſt ſpace to note each dayes variation, and which Pole is eliuated in the end, ſay: This 31. of Iuly, ſaying on an eaſt winde by Gods protection, we had ſight of <hi>Matalena,</hi> and at noone our latitude found by the Sunne pea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring thorow the Vane of your Inſtrument 15. <hi>de.</hi> 3. <hi>mi.</hi> and by the North Starre the next morning the like: ſo at noone the South Eaſt part of <hi>Matalena</hi> South, and the Meridian diſtance from the Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zard 1009 leagues, and diference of longitude 57. <hi>de.</hi> and domini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>co South end 58. <hi>de.</hi> and in your way note thus, for example in a booke by it ſelfe: May the 24. from the 23. at noone, from South to Eaſt 10. <hi>de.</hi> 17. <hi>mi.</hi> latitude 23. <hi>de.</hi> 18. <hi>mi.</hi> ☉. magnitude, A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zimuth 130. <hi>de.</hi> 5. <hi>mi.</hi> True Azimuth 117. <hi>de.</hi> 12. <hi>mi.</hi> the variati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on 12. <hi>de.</hi> 53. <hi>mi.</hi> as in chap. 4. and ſet downe whatſoeuer is re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>markable in your way, as well in the Sea as elſe for example being in the Latitude of 46. S. the body of the Iles of <hi>Babe</hi> North Eaſt, 7 leagues being to the North of the Maine ſhole that lyeth in mid way betweene <hi>Mintain</hi> and Iles <hi>Babe</hi> the Weſt Land of <hi>Babe</hi> Iles North Weſt ½. North 5. leagues from the South Ile of <hi>Babe</hi> towards the Eaſt by North. 20. leagues in Latitude 20. is a dry ſhole that hath to the W. N. W. of it a ſhole or Ledge that is 3. leagues off. Alſo from the dry ſhole is on to the N. E. and from the dry ſhole another to the E. S. E. from the dry ſhole the pike of <hi>Paſamond</hi> Hill 31. <hi>de.</hi> Mag. E. to N. 42. miles, which I found by obſeruation: for being 6. miles from ſhole, my Angle of ſhole and Hill 85. <hi>de.</hi> and the Angle from ſhole to hill and Ship 87 <hi>de.</hi> from Hill to Shole and Ship 8. <hi>de.</hi> by which the diſtance was found, and the Hill appeared thus.</p>
               <p>And for the ſoundings doe thus, Aprill 29. euening <hi>Bautum</hi> hill 17. <hi>de.</hi> 2. <hi>mi.</hi> from S. to W. 14. fatham <hi>Poloubaus</hi> and neare point 26. from S. to W. 14. fatham, at the ſame time A. N.E. by <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. 3. leagues. 4. fatham.</p>
               <p>And now left any ſhould ſay I haue preſcribed many things to others, and can doe nothing my ſelfe; I will make an euident and plaine demonſtration of moſt of theſe things, wherein I ſhall make more eaſie the booke of M. <hi>Thom<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>s Addiſon,</hi> ſometime of <hi>Ratcliffe<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                  </hi> in his life time a good Sea-man, and Mr. of the Ship called the
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:2114:14"/>
                  <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="23" facs="tcp:2114:14"/>
                  <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="18" facs="tcp:2114:15"/>
                  <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="19" facs="tcp:2114:15"/>
                  <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="20" facs="tcp:2114:16"/> 
                  <hi>Palsgraue,</hi> bound to the Eaſt-Indies in the yeere 1624. where he dyed before he had diuulged them: his widdow not knowing what to doe in the matter, and I hearing of the ſame, did purchaſe the ſaid bookes at my owne charge: Thinking it but my duty to quick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>en and raiſe vnto life for the benifit of my Country-men, according to the minde and intent of the Author, that which would haue dy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, or at leſt was like to haue dyed in the ſhell.</p>
               <p>Firſt, the<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>efore as I haue ſpoken of the cirkles of the m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>tteriall Spheare and Globe, ſo I would haue vnderſtand them, though they be deſcribed in plano after this manner. This diſcription is common: but I haue deſcribed the parralell lines with prickes, the horiſon and cirkle of depreſſion with blacke, the almacanter with the other parralells are red, the ſigments within are to ſhew the houre lines as that which croſeth the equator as it were at r<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ct An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gles: that which croſeth the horizon: likewiſe to ſhew the Azimuth and that which croſeth the Ecliptike to ſhew the Longitude and Latitude in the Heauens, and though there 3. inſcribed ſigments be ſomthing hard to doe by Geometricall demonſtration, and for ſo much as they are of ſingular vſe: Therefore when thou wilt finde the true Azimuth, Longitude, or houre on a parralell; Take thy Sector (ſee chap. 6.) and open it to the diſtance of the Semidiame<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter of that parralell in the totall Sine, then take the diſtance in the Sine giuen, and apply it in the paralell from the centor it ſheweth the true place.</p>
               <p>Now I haue giuen a rule before for finding the Sunnes place in the Zodiack, ſee chap. 4. which we will for examples ſake ſuppoſe to be the 30. day Aprill 1629. which is by the Tables of Origanus 19 <hi>de.</hi> 21. <hi>m.</hi> 2. <hi>ſe.</hi> of ♉. and by my rule iuſt 19. <hi>de.</hi> the point in this demonſtration for that place is at B. and this point is found by the cirkle deuided as is before ſpoken of, chap. 4. by taking fromward the poies of the Zodiack, the Sunnes Longitude in degrees, which in this example is 49. <hi>de.</hi> hauing the day of the month, and the ☉. place found, the reſt followeth moſt eaſily: For a parralell drawne to the equator thorow the point at B. ſheweth the declination at C. from A. right Aſcencion B. C. Amplitude A. D. Meridian height F. H. the difference Aſcencionall C. D. and all the reſt followeth, and are meaſured by degrees on the limbe. By the ſame I may ſay
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:2114:16"/> if the declination be giuen, as from A. in the Centor, to C. the ☉ parralell, which by Origanus for the 30. day of Aprill 1629. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> 17. <hi>de.</hi> 46. <hi>m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>.</hi> and by this it is 17. <hi>de.</hi> 30. which is but little leſſe; and that was by the neglect of the minute in the Sunnes Longitude.</p>
               <p>I will giue one demonſtration more, and that ſhall ſuffiſe for this paper, for my purpoſe is to include all this worke within theſe few ſheets.</p>
               <p>This proiection is of that chapter the 4. May the 4. 1629. ☉. place the 23. <hi>d.</hi> 12. <hi>m.</hi> 41. <hi>ſe.</hi> ♉. Origanus Tables, declination 18. <hi>d.</hi> 32. <hi>mi.</hi> N. ☉. Longi. 53. <hi>de.</hi> 12. <hi>mi.</hi> 41. <hi>ſe.</hi> but by this proiection, Suns place 23. <hi>de.</hi> and A. C. declination 18. <hi>de.</hi> 30. <hi>mi.</hi> Longitude 53. <hi>de.</hi> and at B. from A. A. D. the Amplitude <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>8. <hi>de.</hi> E. F. the Meridian height 55. <hi>de.</hi> B. C. right Aſcencion 50. <hi>de.</hi> C. D. diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence Aſcencionall 23. <hi>de.</hi> 0. <hi>mi.</hi> B. G. Obligue Aſcencion 27 <hi>de.</hi> o. <hi>mi.</hi> D. E. ſemydiurnall arke 7. <hi>ho</hi> 32. <hi>mi.</hi> D. E. ſemynoctur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall arke 4. <hi>ho.</hi> 28. D. H. length of twilight 2. <hi>ho.</hi> 4. <hi>mi.</hi> H. E. time from noone to euening ſhut is 9. <hi>ho.</hi> 33. <hi>mi.</hi> that double is the length of the day. 19. <hi>ho.</hi> 6. <hi>mi.</hi> This laſt taken from 24. leaueth the length of the night darke 4. <hi>ho.</hi> 54. <hi>mi.</hi> Sun riſeth at D. 4. <hi>ho.</hi> 28. <hi>mi.</hi> ſeteth at 7. <hi>ho.</hi> 32. <hi>mi.</hi> Time from riſing to ſetting 15. <hi>ho.</hi> 4. from Sun ſetting, to his riſing 8. <hi>ho.</hi> 56. <hi>mi.</hi> Height of the Pole N. R. 51. <hi>de.</hi> 30. <hi>mi.</hi> Though many more propoſitions may be wrought by this kinde of proiection, yet to make ſome good vſe of this marke, the laſt which is the height of the Pole found, ſo that if ye doe but remember the day of the month; which you muſt needs doe by your Kalender in the beginning of this chap. or his declina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion: take his amplitude Azimuth, or Meridionall height, hauing with you your Compaſſes: Compaſſe, croſtafe, Sea-quadrant, Card, and ſome good Tables of the fixed Starres, that yee may vſe them for obſeruation in the night: and by all meanes I would haue you get the reconing of your Ships way by that excellent way of Mr. <hi>Addiſons</hi> of the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> glaſſe, the Log-line, and alſo by what true way ſoeuer the experienced Sea-man can bring to light; and then may you caſt vp your Trauerſe by that excellent way of the Arith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meticall Nauigation, by your Card and Trauerſe bord, and by this Kalender, whoſe vſe is this; Iune the 23. being in Latitude 48. <hi>de.</hi> 14. found by obſeruation, we failed vntill the 24. noone that is
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:2114:17"/> 24. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>. there is the month, day, houre, in the 2 firſt columes vpon a courſe of 33. <hi>de.</hi> from S. to W. 20. leagues, the winde being N. N. E. all this is in the 3. next columes: the Latitude then obſerued to be 47. <hi>de.</hi> 25. <hi>mi.</hi> Longitude in miles 88. from Lizard weſt and the variation 12. <hi>de.</hi> 53. <hi>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>.</hi> depth 90. fatham, (if it were ſound ſo) and theſe in the 2. laſt columes, and from Iuly the 19 in Latitude 17. <hi>de.</hi> 40. <hi>mi.</hi> to Iuly the 21. noone, that is 48. <hi>ho.</hi> we ſayled on a courſe of 18. <hi>de.</hi> from W. to S. 74. leagues. The winde being at E. N E. which brought vs into the Latitude of 16. <hi>de.</hi> 35. <hi>mi.</hi> and into Longitude 1834. miles: or 611 1/<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. leagues W. from Lizard vad 10. <hi>de.</hi> 0. <hi>mi.</hi> Depths 60. fatham, S. W. 7. leagues a Rock, &amp; S. by W. land thus. Note that if you get your height and courſe exactly, it will correct your way, height and way will correct your courſe: courſe and way will correct your height: but ſtriue to doe all as exact as poſible you can, to doe which, note what followeth.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="8" type="chapter">
               <head>Propoſitions of Nauigation, Arethmetically, Geometrically, and Inſtrumentally ſhewed. Chap. <hi>8.</hi>
               </head>
               <div n="1" type="part">
                  <head>
                     <hi>1.</hi> To finde the leagues run on any courſe, the difference of Latitude and courſe being giuen.</head>
                  <p> 
                     <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> AS the ſine of the courſe from the parralell is to the miles in dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ference of Latitude: ſo is the totall ſine to the leagues run.</p>
                  <p> 
                     <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> As the Tangent of the courſe, from the parralell is to the miles in a degree of Latitude; ſo is the Secant of the courſe to the way.</p>
                  <p> 
                     <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> As the totall ſine is to the miles in the difference of Latitude; ſo is the Secant of the courſe, from the Meridian to the miles run.</p>
                  <p> 
                     <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="4"/> As the ſine of the courſe from the Meridian is to the miles in dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ference of Latitude; ſo is the Tangent of the courſe from Meridian to the way.</p>
                  <p> 
                     <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="5"/> Let the Logarithme of the courſe from the parralell be taken out of the Logarithme of miles in difference of Latitude, the remainder is the Logarithme of the miles in way.</p>
                  <p> 
                     <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="6"/> Inſtrumentally by the Sector, take in the equall parts the miles
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:2114:17"/> in difference of Latitude and ſet it ouer in the equall fine<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> of the courſe from the parralell, the Sector ſo opened, take the diſtance ouer in the totall ſigne and that diſtance applyed to the equall parts giueth the miles of way run.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="2" type="part">
                  <head>
                     <hi>2</hi> The difference of Latitude and Longitude giuen to finde the leagues run.</head>
                  <p>SQuare both ſides, then ad the 2. ſquares together and extract <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> the ſquare roote is the miles in way run.</p>
                  <p>Looke which is the greater ſide, either the Lat. or the Lo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>,<note place="margin">This alſo giueth the Rombe.</note> and <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> take his Log. out of the Log. of the leſſer ſide, the remainder giueth the two acute Angles, then let the Log. of either of them be taken out of the Log of the ſide oppoſit: the remainder is the Log. of way I ſhew not how it giueth the Angles but leaue thee to inquire.</p>
                  <p>Open the Sector to a rectangle: then take the miles in Longitude <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> and ſet it on one ſide, the Sector from the Centor in equall parts, and the miles in Latitude on the other ſide: then take the diſtance ouer with a paire of Compaſſes, and apply that diſtance to the e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quall parts, giueth the number of miles in way.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="3" type="part">
                  <head>
                     <hi>3</hi> To finde the difference of Longitude, the courſe and difference of Latitude being giuen.</head>
                  <p>AS the ſum of the courſe from the parralell is to the difference <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> in Latitude, ſo is the fine of the courſe from the Meridian to the difference in Longitude.</p>
                  <p>As the totall ſine is to the difference in Latitude: ſo is the Tan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gent <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> of the courſe from the Meridean to the Longitude.</p>
                  <p>As the Tangent of the courſe, from the parralell to the miles in <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> Latitude: ſo is the totall ſine to the miles in Longitude.</p>
                  <p>As the Secant of the courſe from the parralell is to the difference <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="4"/> of Latitude: ſo is the Secant of the courſe from the Meridian to the Longitude ſought.</p>
                  <p>Take the Logarithme difference of the Angle from the Meridian <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="5"/> out of the Logaritme of the difference of Latitude in miles the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mainder is the logaritme of Longitude in miles.</p>
                  <p>Take the number of equall parts (in the Sector) which are the <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="6"/> difference of Latitude, &amp; fit that diſtance ouer in the liues of ſines
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:2114:18"/> of courſe from the patrid all, and the i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ſtrument opened to that wid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe: the diſtance ouer in the ſine of the courſe from the Meridi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an: that diſtance applyed to the equall parts, ſheweth the Longi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude in miles.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="4" type="part">
                  <head>
                     <hi>4</hi> To finde how many miles off the equator or Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ridian is a degree of Longitude in any parralell of Latitude.</head>
                  <p> 
                     <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> AS the totall ſine is to the miles in a degree of the equator: ſo is the ſine of the compleme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t of Latitude to the miles ſought.</p>
                  <p> 
                     <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> As the Tangent of the Latitude is to a degree in the Meridian: ſo is the line of the Latitude to the miles ſought.</p>
                  <p> 
                     <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> As the Secant of the L<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="3 letters">
                        <desc>•••</desc>
                     </gap>tude is to the miles in the equator or Meridian: ſo is the totall ſine to the miles ſought</p>
                  <p> 
                     <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="4"/> As the Secant of the complement of Latitude is to the miles of Meridian: ſo is the Tangent of the complement of Latitude to the miles, anſwering a degree.</p>
                  <p> 
                     <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="5"/> Let the logarithme of the complement of Latitude be added to the logarithme of miles in a meridians degree; the totall is the lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>garithme of miles ſought.</p>
                  <p> 
                     <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="6"/> Inſtrumentally, take the number of equall parts in a degree of the Meridian or equator by the Sector, &amp; fit them ouer in the ſines totall: then take the diſtance ouer in the ſines of the complement of Latitude, and apply that to the equall parts, ſheweth the miles that make a degre of Longitude in that parralell.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="5" type="part">
                  <head>
                     <hi>5</hi> To finde the Longitude anſwering to a Meri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dian diſtance in any parralell of Latitude.</head>
                  <p> 
                     <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> AS the ſine of the complement of Latitude is to the Meridian diſtance: ſo is the totall ſine to the Longitude.</p>
                  <p> 
                     <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> As the ſine of the Latitude is to the Meridian diſtance: ſo is the Tangent of the Latitude to the Longitude.</p>
                  <p> 
                     <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> As the totall ſine to the Meridian diſtance: ſo is the Secant of Latitude to the Longitude.</p>
                  <pb n="25" facs="tcp:2114:18"/>
                  <p>As the Tangent of the complement to the Meridian diſtance: ſo <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="4"/> is the Secant of the complement to the Longitude.</p>
                  <p>Let the Logarithme of the complement be taken out of the Lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>garithme <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="5"/> of Meridian diſtance, the remainder is Logarithme of Longitude.</p>
                  <p>Take from the ſcale of equall parts in the Sector the Meridian <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="6"/> diſtance; and fit with your Compaſſes in the ſines of the Latitudes complement: then the diſtance taken betweene 90. and 90. apply<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to the ſame ſcale, giueth the Longitude.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="6" type="part">
                  <head>
                     <hi>6</hi> To finde the ſigne of any Arke in any parralell.</head>
                  <p>AS the totall ſine is to the complement: ſo is the ſine giuen <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> in the great Cirkle to the ſine in the Latitude.</p>
                  <p>As the Tangent of Latitude to the ſine of Latitude: ſo is the ſine of the Arke in the great Diameter to the ſine of the Arke in the leſſer.</p>
                  <p>As the Secant of Latitude to the totall ſine: ſo is the ſine in the <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> greater, to the ſine in the leſſer Semy diametor.</p>
                  <p>As the Secant of the complement is to the Tangent thereof: ſo is <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="4"/> the ſine in the greater to the ſine in the leſſer.<note place="margin">This redu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceth Lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gitud miles into degr:</note>
                  </p>
                  <p>Ad to the Logarithme of the Arke giuen, the Logarithme of the complement of Latitude, the totall is the Logarithme of ſine demanded. <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="5"/> 
                  </p>
                  <p>By the Sector let the diſtance from the Centor to the Arke giuen be put ouer in 90. and 90. then the diſtance betweene the ſines of <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="6"/> the complement of Latitude, applyed from the Centor, giueth the Arke whoſe ſine is the demanded.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="7" type="part">
                  <head>
                     <hi>7</hi> By a ſine giuen in a parralell, to finde the Arke.</head>
                  <p>AS the ſine of the complement of the Latitude is to the ſine giuen<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> ſo is the totall ſine to the ſine of the Arke. <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> 
                  </p>
                  <p>As the ſine of the parralell is to the ſine giuen: ſo is the Tangent of the parralell to the ſine of the Arke ſought. <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> 
                  </p>
                  <p>As the totall ſine is to the ſine giuen; ſo is the Secant of parra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lell <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> to the ſine of the Arke ſought.</p>
                  <p>As the Tangent of the complement is to the ſine giuen: ſo is the <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="4"/> Tangent thereof to the ſine of the Arke ſought.</p>
                  <pb n="26" facs="tcp:2114:19"/>
                  <p> 
                     <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="5"/> Out of the Logarithme of the ſine giuen, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>ke the Logarithme of the complement of L<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>i: the reſt is the Logarithme of the ſine.</p>
                  <p> 
                     <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="6"/> By Inſtrument let the diſtance of the ſigne giuen be taken from the Centor and fitted in the ſine of the complement of Latitude;<note place="margin">It reduceth Meridian degrees in to Longi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude.</note> then the diſtance betweene 90. and 90. being ſet from the Centor ſheweth the Arke.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="8" type="part">
                  <head>
                     <hi>8</hi> To finde how many miles on Earth or Sea ſerueth to a minute of time in the Heauen, in any parralell of Latitude.</head>
                  <p>AS the totall ſine is to 15. mile, which ſerueth a minute of time <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> vnder the equator: ſo is the ſine of the complement of Lati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude to the number ſought.</p>
                  <p> 
                     <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> As the Tangent of the Lati<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="3 letters">
                        <desc>•••</desc>
                     </gap>e is to the miles in the equator: ſo is the ſine of the Latitude to the miles ſought.</p>
                  <p> 
                     <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> As the Secant of the Latitude is to the miles in a minute at the equator: ſo is the totall ſine to the miles in a minute of that par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ralell.</p>
                  <p> 
                     <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="4"/> As the Secant of the complement of Latitude, is to the miles in the equator: ſo is the Tangent thereof to the miles in a minute of that parralell.</p>
                  <p> 
                     <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="5"/> Add the Logarithme of the 15. miles, to the Logarithme of the complement of Latitude, the ſumme is the Logarithme of the miles in that parralell.</p>
                  <p> 
                     <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="6"/> By the Inſtrument or Sector, take 15. the miles that ſerue in the equator to a minute of time out of the equall parts, and fit it ouer in the totall ſines: then the diſtance ouer in the ſine of the complement of Latitude applied to the equall parts, ſheweth the miles to a minute in that parralell.</p>
                  <p> 
                     <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> This chapter ha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> ſhewed how to finde the leagues run in any courſe, or the Ships way, and to finde the difference of Longitude, with things thereto pertaining, the next ſheweh.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="9" type="chapter">
               <head>Chapter the <hi>9.</hi>
               </head>
               <div n="9" type="part">
                  <head>
                     <hi>9</hi> To finde the courſe the way and difference of Latitude giuen.</head>
                  <p> 
                     <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> AS the miles in way (or run) is to the totall ſine: ſo is the miles in difference of Latitude to the courſe (or run) his ſine from</p>
                  <gap reason="illegible: missing" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="27" facs="tcp:2114:19"/>
                  <p>As the miles in difference of latit. to the totall ſine, ſo the <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> miles in way to the ſeca. of courſe from meridian.</p>
                  <p>As the difference of latitude to the way, ſo the totall ſine to <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> the ſecant of courſe from meridian.</p>
                  <p>Square both difference of latitude and way, then ſubtract <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="4"/> the leſſer out of the greater, out of the remainder,<note place="margin">This gives the longitude.</note> extract the ſquare roote, then as that roote to the totall ſine, ſo the diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence of latitude to tangent of courſe from paralell.</p>
                  <p>Let the logarithme of way be taken out of the logarithme <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="5"/> of difference of latitude, the remainder is logarithme of courſe from paralell.</p>
                  <p>Take the equall parts in way, and fit over in the totall ſine, <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="6"/> then take the difference of latitude, and fit over in equall ſines, giues the courſe from paralell.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="10" type="part">
                  <head>
                     <hi>10.</hi> To find the courſe, the way, and longitude given.</head>
                  <p>AS the way to the totall ſine, ſo the longitude to courſe <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> from the meridian.</p>
                  <p>As the longitude to the totall ſine, ſo the way to the ſecant <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> of courſe from paralell.</p>
                  <p>As the longitude to the way, ſo the totall ſine to the ſecant <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> of courſe from paralell.</p>
                  <p>Square both longitude and way, then ſubtract the leſſer out <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="4"/> of the greater, out of the remainder extract the ſquare roote,<note place="margin">This gives the latitude.</note> then as that roote to the totall ſine, ſo the longitude to the tangent of courſe from the meridian.</p>
                  <p>Let the logarithme of way be taken out of the logarithme <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="5"/> of difference of longitude, the remainder is logarithme of courſe from the meridian.</p>
                  <p>Let the equall parts in way be fitted over in the totall ſine, <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="6"/> then the long<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>fitted over in equall ſines, gives the courſe from the meridian.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="11" type="part">
                  <head>
                     <hi>11.</hi> To find the courſe, the longitude and latitude g<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>uen.</head>
                  <p>AS the ½ of the 2 ſides added, is to the difference of each <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> ſide, ſo the tangent of ½ the 2 unknowne angles, to the tangent of an arke, which being added to, or taken from ½ the 2 vnknowne angles, gives the courſe.</p>
                  <p>Take the logarithme of the greater ſide, out of the loga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rithme <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/>
                     <pb n="28" facs="tcp:2114:20"/> of the leſſer, the remainder is logarithme of the angle oppoſite to the leſſer ſide.</p>
                  <p>Open the ſector to a rectangle, and take the longitude and latitude, and fit them on 2 ſides from the center; and from thoſe 2 extenſions take the diſtance with a paire of compaſſes, and fit it over in the totall ſine; Then take the longitude, and fit over in equall ſines, gives the courſe from the meridian, but the latitude ſo fitted giues the courſe from paralell.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="12" type="part">
                  <head>
                     <hi>12.</hi> To find the latitude, the courſe and way giuen.</head>
                  <p> 
                     <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> AS the totall ſine to the way, ſo the ſine of courſe from pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ralell to the latitude ſought.</p>
                  <p> 
                     <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> As the ſecant of courſe from paralell to the way, ſo the tan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gent of the ſame to the difference of latitude.</p>
                  <p> 
                     <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> As the ſecant of courſe from the meridian, to the way, ſo the totall ſine to the difference of latitude.</p>
                  <p> 
                     <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="4"/> As the tangent of courſe from the meridian, to the way, ſo the ſine of the ſame courſe to the difference of latitude.</p>
                  <p> 
                     <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="5"/> Adde the logarithme of way to the logarithme of courſe from paralell, the totall is the logarithme of difference of la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titude.</p>
                  <p> 
                     <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="6"/> Take the miles in way, and fit over in the totall ſine, then the diſtance over in the ſine of courſe from paralell, giues the miles in difference of latitude.</p>
                  <p>I haue ſhewed already, chap. 7. how the diſtance from Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ramont hill was found; And as I conceiue, it is eaſie to finde the diſtance of places, if you doe but know the vſe of my Ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble of ſines, tangents and ſecants, proviſo, note that the 3 an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gles of any right-lined triangle is equall to 2 rectangles or 180 degrees.</p>
                  <p>For commonly at ſea, you muſt obſerue the land, ſhore, or whatſoever it is you would know the diſtance from, what angle it maketh with your courſe; as admit 40 degrees, then reckon your ſhips way, ſuppoſe 1000 fathome, and then ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve againe, let your ſecond angle be 100 degrees, then adde 100 deg: &amp; 40 degr: which ſubtract from 180 degr: remainder 40 degr: for the third angle; then haue you 3 angles and one ſide given, by which meanes the other 2 ſides are eaſily had, and conſequently the diſtance.</p>
                  <pb n="29" facs="tcp:2114:20"/>
                  <p>Now if the young beginner be troubled to finde the ſine of an angle, ſo big as 100 degr: let him note what the Table ſaith; ſubtract 90 degr: from 100 degr: the remainder 10 degr: ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tract from 90 degr: reſts So degr: or ſubtract 100 degr: from 180 degr: reſts 80 degr: whoſe ſine in my table is 985; the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther two angles being 40 degr: and 40 degr: their ſines are 643 and 643, and the diſtance 1000 fathome: Now to fetch the diſtance from ſhore ſay, as 643 the ſine of 40 degr: at <hi>c,</hi> found as before, to 1000 fathome, the diſtance from <hi>a</hi> to <hi>b,</hi> the a places of obſervation, ſo 984 the ſine of 80 degr: in the leſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſer quadrant, or 100 degr: in the great, (which is all one) to the diſtance from <hi>a</hi> to <hi>c</hi> 1531 <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>6<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>/61<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> fathome. Another example. 996 ſine of 84 degr: 50. 985 ſine of 80 de. 262 ſine of 15 d: 10. Let your firſt obſervation be at <hi>b</hi> 80 degr: the ſecond at <hi>d</hi> 84 degr: 50, and by your reckoning the diſtance 254 fathome; now it is eaſy by the former rule to find the angle at <hi>c</hi> 15 degr: 10: then ſay if 262 giue 254, what giues 985, facit <hi>c d</hi> 954 110/<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="3 letters">
                        <desc>•••</desc>
                     </gap>: And as 262 to 254, ſo 996 to the diſtance <hi>b c.</hi> So that it is all one whether the angles be right, or obtuce, or acute, if they be all acute, there is no more to doe but take the ſines out of my table as in the figure K, and no more, if one be a rectangle, then the other 2 are acute, but if an angle be obtuce, as in the figure L, the angle at <hi>b</hi> 100 degr: doe by that angle whatſoe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver it be, as in the firſt example; here becauſe the angles at <hi>a</hi> and <hi>c</hi> are equall, therefore the diſtance from <hi>b</hi> to <hi>c</hi> is 1000 fathome.</p>
                  <p>But by the ſecond example, it is but 965 77/<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="3 letters">
                        <desc>•••</desc>
                     </gap>, therefore the angle at <hi>d</hi> was not truly taken; for what 965 77/<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="3 letters">
                        <desc>•••</desc>
                     </gap> is in propor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion to 1000, ſo is the angle at <hi>d</hi> to the true angle: which muſt needs be more then 84 degr: 50, and the angle at <hi>c</hi> leſſe then 15 degr: 10 and conſequently the ſide <hi>c d</hi> is more then 954 120/<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="3 letters">
                        <desc>•••</desc>
                     </gap>. And further you may note, if you have obſerved ſo well that the angles be truly taken, then have you not reckoned your ſhips way truly; and ſo you may ſee that one of theſe doth correct the other, as in the end of the 7 chapter.</p>
                  <p>And you may fetch a diſtance by Geometricall protraction, as in chap. 4. ſuppoſe you would know the diſtance from <hi>c</hi>
                     <pb n="30" facs="tcp:2114:21"/> and <hi>b</hi> to <hi>f,</hi> in the figure <hi>m,</hi> firſt having drawne the angle <hi>b e f,</hi> then reckon your ſhips way from <hi>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>
                     </hi> to <hi>b</hi> 
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>00 fathome, and ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving laid downe ſo much by your ſcale and compaſſes, (ſee pag. 12) you ſhall obſerue to lay the line <hi>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> b</hi> right in the courſe your ſhip went, with <hi>b</hi> next your eye, and <hi>e</hi> towards the place of your firſt obſervation; then from <hi>b</hi> draw another line to <hi>f,</hi> and that line will interſect with the line <hi>a f</hi> at <hi>f,</hi> and then you may meaſure the diſtance; as in this example <hi>b f</hi> is 100 fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thom, and <hi>e f</hi> is 140 fathom.</p>
                  <p>The next thing that will trouble the young beginner, is the propoſitions in theſe 8 and 9 chapters, which are moſt eaſily performed, becauſe the demonſtration is ſo plaine.</p>
                  <p>Firſt therfore as in all plain triangles, the ſides are in propor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion one to another, as the ſubtences of the angles oppoſite, or as the ſines of the angles oppoſite to thoſe ſides. Example in the inſcribed triangle: <hi>A</hi> the angle at <hi>b</hi> is in proportion to the ſide <hi>c d</hi> or arke <hi>c g d,</hi> as the angle <hi>c</hi> to the ſide <hi>b d,</hi> or arke <hi>b d e,</hi> and ſo is the angle <hi>d</hi> to the ſide <hi>b c,</hi> or arke <hi>b f c.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>So note that in all rectangled right-lined triangles, the two containing ſides of the rectangle ſtand perpendicular one up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the end of another: Therefore if you put the leaſt ſide for radius or totall ſine, as in the figure <hi>b,</hi> the other ſide will be the tangent, and the ſubtending ſide of the rectangle will be the ſecant; or if you put the greater ſide for radius, the leaſt will be the tangent, and the ſubtence the ſecant, or you may put the ſubtence for radius, as in the figure <hi>c</hi> is done.</p>
                  <p>It is manifeſt then that any ſide may be put for the totall ſine: Firſt, if you put the ſubtending ſide for radius, as in the figure <hi>d,</hi> let <hi>a b</hi> be part of a meridian, and <hi>a c</hi> part of a paralell; then is the angle at <hi>b</hi> the courſe from the meridian, and the angle at <hi>c</hi> is the courſe from paralell.</p>
                  <p>Then if the difference of latitude <hi>a b,</hi> and courſe, that is the angle at <hi>b</hi> or <hi>c</hi> be given, you may finde the leagues runne, or diſtance <hi>b c,</hi> as in the firſt reſolution Arithmeticall.</p>
                  <p>Or if you put the longer ſide <hi>a b</hi> for radius, then ſay as the totall ſine <hi>a b</hi> to the difference of latitude <hi>a b,</hi> ſo the ſecant <hi>b c</hi> of courſe, <hi>b</hi> from the meridian, to the diſtance <hi>b c;</hi> if you put
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:2114:21"/> the leaſt ſide for radius, ſay as the tangent <hi>a b</hi> of courſe <hi>c</hi> from paralell, to <hi>a b</hi> the difference of latitude, ſo <hi>b c</hi> the ſecant of the ſame courſe, to <hi>b c</hi> the diſtance. Let this ſu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>ice for the firſt propoſition chap. 8.</p>
                  <p>But if you demaund the difference of longitude, the latitude and courſe being given, you may doe it by the firſt or ſecond example Arithmeticall in this chapter. page 29; or if you put the longer ſide <hi>b c</hi> for radius, ſay, as the courſe <hi>c</hi> to <hi>a b,</hi> ſo the courſe <hi>b</hi> to <hi>a c</hi> the longitude: but if you put the ſide <hi>a b</hi> for radius, ſay, as the totall ſine to the difference of latitude, ſo the tangent <hi>a c</hi> to the difference of longitude: if the leaſt ſide be put for radius, ſay, as the tangent <hi>a b</hi> to the difference of lati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude, ſo the totall ſine to the difference of longitude. And this ſufficeth for the Geometricall demonſtrotion of the third pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſition, chap. 8.</p>
                  <p>And now you ſee how the proportionall numbers doe a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſe, it is eaſie to take them out of the Table, and worke them Arithmetically; and what is ſaid of theſe propoſitions may be ſaid of all the reſt by the very ſame reaſon; except the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond propoſition chap. 8, and the 11 propoſition in this chap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter page 27: the firſt of theſe is done as in <hi>Earlid</hi> 1.47. or thus Arithmetically.</p>
                  <p>Let the line <hi>a</hi> be 3 leagues of longitude and the line <hi>b</hi> 4 leagues of latitude, firſt multiply 3 <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> 3, it is 9, and 4 into 4 is 16, which added is 25, the ſquare roote is 5, for 5 times 5 is 25, and this is equall to the line <hi>c,</hi> the ſhippes way.</p>
                  <p>The Geometricall demonſtration is this, ſet the line <hi>a</hi> per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pendicular vpon the line <hi>b,</hi> as in the figure <hi>f,</hi> then draw the line <hi>c,</hi> and it is 5 the ſhippes way.</p>
                  <p>There is another way of demonſtration, by adding the ſides of the ſquares into one; alſo if the way and longitude had beene given, to ſubtract the one out of the other Geome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trically, the remainder is the difference of latitude: if the way and latitude had beene given, then the ſide of the remainder is the difference of longitude, <hi>Euclid</hi> 1.47. <hi>theor.</hi> 33. 6.31. <hi>theor.</hi> 21.</p>
                  <p>The next ſhould be of the 11 propoſition, but I ſuppoſe he
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:2114:22"/>
                     <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                        <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <pb n="31" facs="tcp:2114:22"/>
                     <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                        <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <pb n="32" facs="tcp:2114:23" rendition="simple:additions"/> that underſtands that is more than an ignorant man, therefore whoſoever will learne that, with the extraction of the ſquare and cube roote, or any thing elſe that is in my booke, or a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny of thoſe things that I have ſet out in any of my bills; let them come to my dwelling, and I will ſatiſfie their de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maund ſo farre forth as God ſhall inable mee: where youth may bee taught, dieted and lodged for reaſonable conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="10" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. X.</hi> Of the motion of the Moone, and comming into the Harbour.</head>
               <p>I Might here have added many and manifold propoſiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, and chiefly thoſe which doe concerne the great cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cle diſtance betweene any two places howſoever ſcitu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ate; but I will firſt ſee thy kinde acceptance of this: which if you receive thankfully, I ſhall be ready to ſhew thee many more to thy great ſatiſfaction, with the Geome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tricall demonſtration, which I have gathered into a booke in Folio.</p>
               <p>And now I will finiſh this worke with the Moones mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion; ſuppoſing you are come in ſight of your wiſhed port in ſafety: which I doe heartily wiſh to all honeſt Seamen of my Country, that travell the ſeas to good ends.</p>
               <p>And admit you are in a ſtrange coaſt, you may the better come to finde the time of a full ſea, at a ſpring tide, to bring your good ſhippe over a barre or ſhole: ſo I ſhall end my worke where Mr. <hi>Addiſon</hi> began his: then having read this, you may reade his which is hereto joyned; giving you to underſtand, if you learne well theſe propoſitions of mine, they will make even the hardeſt things in his booke eaſy for thy underſtanding.</p>
               <pb n="33" facs="tcp:2114:23"/>
               <p>Let the full ſea at your place of being be at a S Moone on the day of conjunction as at <hi>a,</hi> and the Sunne going in 4 degrees, as from <hi>a</hi> to <hi>c,</hi> the Moone removing in the meane time 48 de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grees from the Sunne, as to <hi>d,</hi> doth make 3 houres 12 mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nutes after noone for the time of high water; and in 16 dayes more the Sunne going from <hi>c</hi> to <hi>e,</hi> that is <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>0 degrees from <hi>a:</hi> in the meane time the Moone going from <hi>d</hi> to <hi>f,</hi> that is 260 degrees from <hi>a,</hi> which maketh 17 houres 20 minutes, then ſubſtract 12 houres 0 minutes from 17 houres 20 minutes, the remainder 5 houres 20 minutes; out of which take 1 houre 20 minutes for the time of the Sunnes motion in 20 dayes, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mainder 4 a clocke for the true time of full ſea the Moone be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing 20 dayes olde; if you perceive not the reaſon hereof in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quire futher, and ſo you may examine the truth hereof.</p>
               <p>Therefore to the ignorant and honeſt Seaman I ſay, joyne theſe things in practiſe with thoſe things thy Maſter doth teach thee at ſea: And to thoſe things you learne at ſea by ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perience joyne the practiſe of the things taught in this booke, and you ſhall be able in ſhort time, through Gods grace, no doubt, to take charge thy ſelfe to thy great commendations.</p>
               <p>To conclude, you may doe moſt of the things taught in this booke as afore ſpoken of chapter the 4, with rular and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſſes; which if you practiſe and make your ſelfe able to per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forme, (wiſhing to every good man that is willing to follow theſe rules, that I were at his elbow to make him a more plaine demonſtration) he ſhall be able in a ſhort time, to doe ſuch ſervice, which without thoſe will not be performed in ten times ſo much time.</p>
               <p>And ſo I pray thee to accept of this my labour, for unto ſuch as are ignorant and honeſt, that would learne, onely doe I write this booke: And be ſure to reade it all before you judge, ſo ſhall you ſee that ſuch a thing there is, then reade it over againe, and you ſhall ſee what manne<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> of thing it is, ſo you may judge of the good will of the Authour, and reade it over the third time to thy ſingular profit.</p>
               <pb facs="tcp:2114:24"/>
               <p>As in <hi>Eccleſiaſticus</hi> chapter the 22. verſe <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>3, it i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> neighbour, ſo I ſay to thee of thy friend to Navigation; <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Be faithfull to him in his poverty, that you may rejoyce with him in his prosperity, abide ſtedfast with him in the time of his trouble, that you may be heire with him in</hi> (this his little book) <hi>his heritage: for a meane eſtate is not alwayes to be contemned, nor the rich that is fooliſh to be had in admiration.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Now I beſech Almighty God of his mercy in Chriſt Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus, that wee may ſo profit in Chriſts ſchoole, that wee may bee able thereby to paſſe the waves of this ſea of glaſſe, that we may all arrive at the haven of eternall happineſſe. <hi>Amen.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:2114:24"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
